Guide to the National Council of Jewish Women, Pittsburgh Section Records, 1894-2011 AIS.1964.40
ULS Archives & Special Collections
National Council of Jewish Women (NCJW), Pittsburgh Section, Records
1894-2011
ULS Archives & Special Collections
National Council of Jewish Women. Pittsburgh Section
AIS.1964.40
139.71 Linear Feet (120 boxes, 5 volumes, and 8 drawers of cassette tapes)
The National Council of Jewish Women (NCJW), Pittsburgh Section Records, consist of organizational records, including correspondence, memorabilia, reports, minutes, photographs, and oral histories for the period 1894 to 1997. The bulk of the records are from the NCJW Pittsburgh Section, however, there are some materials in the collection regarding NCJW state and national activities. Digital reproductions of the audio component of the oral history project are available online.
History
The National Council of Jewish Women (NCJW) was founded in 1893 at the Jewish Women's Congress of the Columbian Exposition in Chicago. Mrs. Pauline Rosenberg founded the Pittsburgh Section in 1894 and this became the fourth section of NCJW. The Pittsburgh Section was called the Columbian Council until May 1906. The Pittsburgh Section has been devoted to many activities at the local, state, and national levels. Activities have included fundraising, education, political and social reforms, workshops and institutes. Almost all of these activities directly assist Jewish causes.
The Pittsburgh Section has always been dedicated to establishing programs to provide quality education. They created the first free kindergarten in Pittsburgh and a religious school for the children of immigrants in Pittsburgh's Hill District. This was the first of a network of Sunday Schools run jointly with Temple Rodef Shalom Sisterhood for many years. Their varied programs for children resulted in the establishment of the Columbian School, a full-fledged settlement house in its own quarters in 1900. Columbian School, later Columbian School and Settlement, became the Irene Kaufmann Settlement (IKS) in 1909. A new building and endowment fund was given by the parents of the late Irene Kaufmann, Henry and Theresa Kaufmann. The Pittsburgh Section also had volunteers run an informal Americanization class for immigrants. This later became a fully staffed and organized Evening School, the first of its kind in the Pittsburgh area. The "ethnic revival" of the late sixties led to a renewed interest in Jewish education, and in the 1970s Pittsburgh Section volunteers catalogued the Judaic holdings of local libraries. The Pittsburgh Section's interest in public education has continued unabated through the decades.
The Pittsburgh Section has also been involved in many public health issues. The Columbian School introduced the first visiting nurse to Pittsburgh. The second nurse hired for the job in 1902, Miss Anna B. Heldman, stayed until her death in 1940. She sponsored many public health measures with Pittsburgh Section's aid. Involvement in public health enterprises at the local and national level continues into the present. The Pittsburgh Section assists with the Red Cross, Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Veteran's Administration Volunteer Service, Council House Rehabilitation of Psychiatric Patients, Department of Health Infant Care at Arsenal Health Center, and the Pittsburgh Race for the Cure.
In addition to the above activities the Pittsburgh Section has been involved in countless activities, including the establishment of various committees to study political and social reforms; published guides and reference works on taxes and other subjects; work for civil rights, the handicapped, and the elderly; shown great interest in developing projects in Israel since its founding in 1948; and was in the forefront of "preventive philanthropy" activities, making it possible for people to avoid charity by becoming self-supporting.
The NCJW Pittsburgh Section has also taken a special interest with issues concerning women. The Pittsburgh Section founded the Council House for Working Girls and has had a long-standing cooperative relationship with many women's organizations, including the Federation of Women's Clubs, the Pittsburgh Conference of Jewish Women's Organizations, Women in Community Service Corporation, and Women in the Urban Crisis of Western Pennsylvania.
Along with the serious business there has always been a lighter side to the Pittsburgh Section's activities. Early programs of the Section's include musical events, dramatics, and socials. During the 1940s and 1950s fun and fundraising were combined in carnivals, dances, and shows.
Related Material
Allegheny County Committee on Fair Employment Practices Records, 1945-1954, AIS.1969.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
American Service Institute Records, ca.1920-1961, AIS.1963.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Committee on Immigration and Naturalization of Allegheny County Records, 1953-1967, AIS.1968.09, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Congress of Clubs and Club Women of Western Pennsylvania Records, 1890-1963, AIS.1964.10, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County Records, 1943-1950, AIS.1968.14a, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Housing Authority of the City of Pittsburgh Records, 1937-1953, AIS.1966.08, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Jewish Community Relations Council Records, 1928-1959, AIS.1965.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Oliver M. Kaufmann Photograph Collection-The History of the Jewish Community Center of Pittsburgh, 1912-1969, AIS.1978.12, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System Pittsburgh Conference of Jewish Women's Organizations Records, 1923-1963, AIS.1968.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Rauh Family Papers, AIS.1966.12, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Lillian A. Friedberg Papers, 1904-1975, AIS.2000.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the organizational records of the NCJW Pittsburgh Section (variously Columbian Council and Greater Pittsburgh Section) founded in 1894. This collection includes correspondence, memorabilia, reports, minutes, photographs, and oral histories for the period 1894 to 1997. The bulk of the records are from the NCJW Pittsburgh Section, however there are some materials in the collection regarding NCJW state and national activities. However, the first three decades of the Pittsburgh Section history are not adequately represented in these records. The minutes and reports were probably kept in the executives' homes and were lost at their deaths. This history must be reconstructed from the historical summaries and yearbooks. The first fifteen years of Pittsburgh Section history are covered in Ida Cohen Selavan book, The Columbian Council of Pittsburgh, 1894-1909: A Case Study of Adult Immigrant Education, and unpublished doctoral dissertation written in 1976.
There are fairly complete records for programs begun in the 1920s to the 1990s, as well as available historic and organizational materials. The Pittsburgh Section has also been associated with many organizations on the local, state, and national level, including the German Jewish Children's Aid Committee, American Service Institute, Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Allegheny County Council on Civil Rights, Allegheny County Federation of Women's Clubs, Women in Community Services Corporation, Women in the Urban Crisis of Western Pennsylvania, American Jewish Conference, American Jewish Congress, Irene Kaufmann Settlement, Jewish Community Relations Council, Jewish Social Service Bureau, Pittsburgh Conference of Jewish Women's Organizations, United Jewish Federation, and Young Men and Women's Hebrew Association. Materials on these organizations can be found throughout the collection.
Also found in the various series is correspondence with prominent Americans such as Eleanor Roosevelt, Henry A. Wallace, U.S. and State Senators and Representatives, Governors, Mayors, Clergymen, and local dignitaries. Besides correspondence, the collection also includes one tape recording of the First Annual Louis Rosenthal Legislative Institute, autograph albums dedicated to Section leaders, unmounted photographs of people involved in Section projects, and a series of scrapbooks with newspaper clippings documenting Section projects from the mid-1920s through the 1950s.
Of particular importance to the Pittsburgh Section has been their Oral History Project initiated in 1968. Volunteers for the project interviewed over 200 Jewish residents of Pittsburgh who had immigrated between 1890-1924. The interviewees were tape recorded and filled out questionnaires. The project resulted in the publication of a book in 1972, By Myself I'm a Book! An Oral History of the Immigrant Jewish Experience in Pittsburgh. A second project, carried out between 1974 and 2001, inspired the book My Voice was Heard. Tapes from both projects have been digitized and are available online on the website, Pittsburgh and Beyond: The Experience of the Jewish Community. For more information on the NCJW Oral History Projects, refer to Series XXVIII.
In June 2011, NCJW Oral History Project Co-Chairs, Marcia Frumerman and Marlene Haus, donated additional material relating to the NCJW Oral History Projects. Included in this donation were further materials for both Oral History Project I & II and extensive files on curriculum and course development based on the oral history interviews. The new materials also include information on creating and standardizing abstracts and indices to create Pittsburgh and Beyond: The Experience of the Jewish Community a guide to the oral history interviews. The new materials mostly have been added to the existing Series XXVIII. NCJW Oral History Project. New material has also been added to Series XVI. Subject Files. Further scope notes are found in both series.
The NCJW Pittsburgh Section has made many deposits to the Archives Service Center since 1964, however, all additions to the collection are located under AIS.1964.40.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into the following series:
Series I. History, 1894-1983
Series II. Charter, By-laws, and Organization, 1894-1974
Series III. Governing Bodies, 1914-1973
Series IV. Officers, 1894-1978
Series V. Administration, 1921-1977
Series VI. Fundraising, 1927-1979
Series VII. Education, 1894-1974
Series VIII. Philanthropic Activities, 1901-1975
Series IX. Community and Oversees Services, 1927-1980
Series X. Health and Welfare Services, 1946-1973
Series XI. Political Action, 1929-1979
Series XII. Jewish Affiliations, 1928-1975
Series XIII. Affiliation Networks, 1896-1976
Series XIV. Photographs, Scrapbooks, and Record Books, 1960-1973
Series XV. Publications and Organizational Records, 1959-1987
Series XVI. Subject Files, 1943-1995
Series XVII. Organizational Records, 1934-1989
Series XVIII. Council Journals, 1949-1954
Series XIX. Publications and Papers, 1967-1976
Series XX. Scrapbooks, 1944-1990
Series XXI. Photographs and Slides, 1933-1990
Series XXII. Awards, 1954-1993
Series XXIII. Organizational Records, 1947-1990
Series XXIV. Photographs, 1970-1989
Series XXV. Organizational Records, 1956-1994
Series XXVI. Membership and Volunteer Service, 1956-1993
Series XXVII. Photographs, 1990-2003
Series XXVIII. NCJW Oral History Projects, 1968-2001
Series XXIX. Scrapbooks and Posters, 1960-1989
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Subsequent additions made in 1976, 1984, 1992, 2002, 2005 and 2011.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the National Council of Jewish Women on September 9, 1964.
Previous Citation
National Council of Jewish Women, Pittsburgh Section Records, 1894-2011, AIS.1964.40, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
National Council of Jewish Women, Pittsburgh Section Papers, 1894-2003, AIS.1964.40, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://digital.library.pitt.edu/n/ncjw/.
Oral histories (Document genres); Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Emigration and immigration; Pennsylvania -- Emigration and immigration; Women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Oral history; Ethnic groups; Jews -- Social life and customs; Women; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- History; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Interviews; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Interviews; Societies; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Social conditions; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Charities; Interviews; Jewish women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; National Council of Jewish Women. Pittsburgh Section. South Hills Branch; National Council of Jewish Women. Pittsburgh Section
- History, 1894-1983; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains historical materials relating to the founding of the NCJW Pittsburgh Section. However, many materials have been lost. The little material that is available includes a condensed history of the Section written by Mrs. Amelia Zugsmith, President of the Pittsburgh Section from 1922-1925 and Council Historian. She prepared the history "from all available sources of information," including records of meetings, newspaper clippings and interviews, and this was updated periodically through 1929. However, the source materials referred to in the history are no longer available, except some early correspondence (1894-1901). A number of other histories were written in the 1940s from Mrs. Zugsmith's summary, but some contain errors. This series also contains materials devoted to the special anniversaries of the Pittsburgh Section, including the 35th, 50th, 75th, 80th, and 90th.
  - General, 1.
    - 1894-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1944-1955 (includes report by Historian) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - 1894-197? (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Historic Anniversaries, 2.
    - 35th Anniversary,; 50th Anniversary, 1929 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Eleanor Roosevelt, Henry A. Wallace, and U.S. Representative Samuel A. Weiss (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 60th Anniversary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 70th Anniversary, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 75th Anniversary; 80th Anniversary; 90th Anniversary, 1968-1969, 1973, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Charter, By-laws, and Organization, 1894-1974; II.
  Series II contains organizational records. While there is a constitution for the National Council of Jewish Women, sections are governed by their own by-laws and standing rules. These are frequently revised and this series contains many revisions from 1926 onward. Mrs. Zugsmith's historic survey mentions, "the Pittsburgh Section, NCJW took out a charter and became an incorporated body... in May, 1909." No trace of this charter has been found to date. This series also includes the incorporation papers of 1921.
  - Incorporation Papers (originals held by NCJW), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - By-laws and revisions, 1928-1974 (intermittent) (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Standing rules, policies, and procedures, 1894-1971 (intermittent) (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Committee on by-laws and rules, 1920-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
  - Organizational charts, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Governing Bodies, 1914-1973; III.
  Series III contains materials relating to the Board, committees, and projects of the Pittsburgh Section. In its earliest years the Pittsburgh Section was run by just a few women serving as officers. As membership grew and various projects were undertaken, committee and Board members were elected and appointed to fulfill certain governance functions. The oldest and most continuous records available are from the Executive Board (1914-1917, 1925-1973). The formation of an Executive Committee consisted of a President, Vice President, Corresponding, Recording, and Financial Secretaries, Auditor, Historian, and five Members of the Executive Board (1926-1969, 1971). A Steering Committee, which was made up of the Executive Committee plus appointed members, served as an Advisory Committee to the President from 1936-1946. An Advisory Committee, whose minutes date from 1946 was replaced by the Executive Committee in 1964, although references to the Advisory Committee continue to 1971. There are also materials from the Board of Directors, an honorary function for the section from 1950 (1933-1960).
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1.
    - Executive Board Minutes, November 1914-February 1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1946-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3-20)
    - Minutes, 1964-1975 (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - Executive Committee, 2.
    - Minutes, 1926-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lists of members, 1946-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Steering Committee, 3.
    - Minutes, 1947-1956 (some undated) (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Lists of members, 1946-1956 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Committee, 4.
    - Minutes and recommendations, 1936-1963, 1966-1973 (some undated) (Box 6, Folder 9-14)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Lists of members, 1961-1971 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 5.
    - Minutes, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Lists of members,, and correspondence, 1950-1958 1935-1947 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Officers, 1894-1978; IV.
  Series IV contains materials for the number of officers that have servied the Pittsburgh Section over the years. During its first year the Pittsburgh Section functioned with four officers, a President, Vice-President, Treasurer, and Secretary. By May of 1895, the job of Secretary was divided into two positions the Recording and Assistant Secretary. In later years other positions were added, including Auditor (1906), a second Vice-President (1908), and a Financial Secretary (1911). Third and fourth Vice-Presidents were added in 1913 and 1918, but it is unclear whether the positions were re-elected.
  It is only from the mid 1920s, with the election of Mrs. Lillian Freund as President, that minutes, records and reports were maintained. Reports and minutes from annual meetings, sometimes called "President's Day" or "Volunteer Recognition Day," include the President's report. The President's report can be found in the President Files. Material on both are included in the files. The annual reports were published in the yearbooks, reports missing in this series may be found there.
  A separate folder has been assigned to the correspondence and papers of each President even where no papers have yet been located. Folders are arranged chronologically by term of office.
  - President Files, 1.
    - Annual Reports (some may contain slides), 1934-1970 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - Minutes, 1926-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5-9)
    - Ballots and nominations, 1906-1967 (intermittent) (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Invitations, 1960-1968 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - President's Day, 1925-1972 (Box 7, Folder 12-20)
    - President's Day (continued), 1925-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Volunteer Recognition Day, 1958-1975 (Box 8, Folder 5-8)
    - Correspondence files for each President, 1894-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1-29)
    - Historic letters to Presidents, 1894-1975 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Recording Secretary Files, 2.
    - Reports, 1928-1958 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Notarized statement, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Corresponding Secretary Files, 3.
    - Reports, 1927-1953 (intermittent) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Financial Secretary Files, 4.
    - Reports, 1946-1973 (Box 10, Folder 5-13)
  - Treasurer Files, 5.
    - Reports, 1927-1970 (Box 11, Folder 1-20)
    - Reports (continued), 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Audits, 1941, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Ledgers, 1959-1964 (Box 12, Folder 5-9)
    - Employee records, 1954-1964 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
- Administration, 1921-1977; V.
  Series V contains materials of the Executive Board. During its first decade of existence the Section administered all activities via the Executive Board. At that time budgets were usually drawn up on an ad hoc basis. However, in its second decade the Pittburgh Section's membership increased, committees proliferated, and the collection of dues and the allocation of funds became more organized. A budget of a few hundred dollars in 1904 had grown to $20,000 by 1915.
  By 1921, there were 54 committees and it was decided to divide them among nine departments. The "departments" were renamed "bureaus" and reorganized in the late 1940s. They were renamed "departments" again in the early 1960s. In 1962, the Pittsburgh Section was decentralized into divisions based on place of residence and meeting time (e.g. Evening Division). However, in April of 1970 the divisions were dissolved.
  Because of these administrative permutations and combinations, these series are based on function rather than subject. The series contains files and reports relating to finance, membership (including oversized ledgers), policy and personnel, and program, publicity and public relations.
  - Finance Committee, 1.
    - Minutes, 1921-1971 (Box 12, Folder 12-19)
    - Reports, 1932-1968 (intermittent) (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Lists of members, 1943-1952 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Budgets, 1923-1967 (Box 12, Folder 22-29)
    - Investments and insurance policies, 1932-1973 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Membership Committee
      - Reports, 1933-1972 (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
      - Minutes, 1930-1962 (Box 13, Folder 4-7)
      - Correspondence, Membership Vice-President, 1951-1973 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Campaigns, 1943-1960 (Box 13, Folder 9-11)
      - Report, Membership Review Committee, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Extension, 1945-1961 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Fifty-year membership party, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Directory of new members, 1922-1937 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Lists of members, 1951-1971 (Box 13, Folder 16-23)
      - Lists of deceased members, 1953-1967 (Box 13, Folder 24)
      - Ledgers, 1947-1961 (Box 13, Volume 1-6)
    - Policy and Personnel
      - Reports, 1927-1934 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)